Guide to the Orville W. Crowder's Cheasapeake and Ohio Canal collection, "1927-1997 MS2152
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Orville W. Crowder's Chesapeake and Ohio Canal collection
1927-1997
1951-1974
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Crowder, Orville W.
MS2152
3 Linear Feet
This collection contains newspaper clippings, newsletters, photographs, maps, guide books, certificates, color slides, reports, pins, membership cards, and other memorabilia. The material dates from 1927-1997, but the bulk of the material dates from 1951-1974. The material was collected by Orville Wright Crowder and relates to his tour and preservation work on the Chesapeake and Ohio Canal. Much of the materials consist of maps of Maryland, Pennsylvania, Virginia and Ohio.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Donald Messersmith 1/26/2006 (accession 2006.032)
Historical or Biographical Note
Orville Wright Crowder (1904 - 1974) was a nature enthusiast that worked as a historian and guide for the Chesapeake and Ohio Canal Association from 1933 - 1974. His contributions to the association included helping to measure and describe the Chesapeake and Ohio Canal, creating various clubs and organizations and leading a daily bird tour. His most notable achievements outside of the C&O Association include helping create, measure and describe the Appalachian trail, becoming the third person to hike the entire length of the trail and founding the World Nature Tours and the World Nature Club. His extensive nature tours allowed him to set foot on each country in the world except five as well as hike the highest points of each state within the United States except for Alaska and Hawaii.
Collection Scope and Content
This collection contains newspaper clippings, newsletters, photographs, maps, guide books, certificates, color slides, reports, pins, membership cards, and other memorabilia. The material dates from 1927-1997, but the bulk of the material dates from 1951-1974. The material was collected by Orville Wright Crowder and relates to his tour and preservation work on the Chesapeake and Ohio Canal. Much of the materials consist of maps of Maryland, Pennsylvania, Virginia and Ohio.
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for research.
Arrangement note
Folders are organized alphabetically; topographical maps are arranged in order of the canal's route. This collection is not divided into series.
Chesapeake and Ohio Canal (Md. and Washington, D.C.); Photographs; Chesapeake and Ohio Canal National Historical Park; Membership; Color slides; Guidebooks; Maps; Chesapeake & Ohio Canal Association -- Pictorial works
- Along the Towpath newsletter, 03/20/1970-10/1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Along the Towpath newsletter, 06/1996-12/1996 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- The Amazing Pennsylvania Canals, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- C and O Canal National Monument staff, circa 1962 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- C and O Canal of Cumberland, Maryland, Inc., 07/28/1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- C and O Canal memorabilia, circa 1924 - circa 1971 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Chesapeak and Ohio Canal Association, undated and 01/30/1997 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Clippings, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Collection of maps of the Chesapeake and Ohio Canal, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Death claims Orville Crowder, 09/1974 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Gude seeks to preserve C and O Canal, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Membership cards, 1964-1968 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Photograph of Ernest Grubb, Orville Crowder, and Supreme Court Justice William Douglas, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Photographs of Harpers Ferry vicinity, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Public information meeting to discuss C and O Canal, 05/1972 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Slides of C and O Canal, circa 1954 - circa 1959 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- A Study of the History of the Potomac River Valley, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Towpath Guide - Sections 1 and 2, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Towpath Guide - Sections 3 and 4, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- C and O Canal Topographical map 1 - Washington West, 1951 (Map-folder 1, Item 1)
- C and O Canal Topographical map 2 - Falls Church, 1951 (Map-folder 1, Item 2)
- C and O Canal Topographical map 3 - Rockville, 1951 (Map-folder 1, Item 3)
- C and O Canal Topographical map 4 - Seneca, 1952 (Map-folder 1, Item 4)
- C and O Canal Topographical map 5 - Sterling, 1952 (Map-folder 1, Item 5)
- C and O Canal Topographical map 6 - Leesburg, 1952 (Map-folder 1, Item 6)
- C and O Canal Topographical map 7 - Waterford, 1952 (Map-folder 1, Item 7)
- C and O Canal Topographical map 8 - Poolesville, 1952 (Map-folder 1, Item 8)
- C and O Canal Topographical map 9 - Buckeystown, 1952 (Map-folder 1, Item 9)
- C and O Canal Topographical map 10 - Point of Rocks, 1955 (Map-folder 1, Item 10)
- C and O Canal Topographical map 11 - Harpers Ferry, 1955 (Map-folder 2, Item 1)
- C and O Canal Topographical map 13 - Keedysville, 1953 (Map-folder 2, Item 2)
- C and O Canal Topographical map 15 - Williamsport, 1953 (Map-folder 2, Item 3)
- C and O Canal Topographical map 16 - Hedgesville, 1955 (Map-folder 2, Item 4)
- C and O Canal Topographical map 17 - Clear Springs, 1955 (Map-folder 2, Item 5)
- C and O Canal Topographical map 18 - Big Pool, 1958 (Map-folder 2, Item 6)
- C and O Canal Topographical map 19 - Cherry Run, 1951 (Map-folder 2, Item 7)
- C and O Canal Topographical map 20 - Hancock, 1951 (Map-folder 2, Item 8)
- C and O Canal Topographical map 21 - Bellegrove, 1951 (Map-folder 2, Item 9)
- C and O Canal Topographical map 22 - Great Cacapon, 1958 (Map-folder 2, Item 10)
- C and O Canal Topographical map 23 - Artemas, 1951 (Map-folder 2, Item 11)
- C and O Canal Topographical map 24 - Paw Paw, 1951 (Map-folder 3, Item 1)
- C and O Canal Topographical map 25 - Old Town, 1951 (Map-folder 3, Item 2)
- C and O Canal Topographical map 26-29, undated (Map-folder 3, Item 3)
- Map of Allegany County, 1953 (Map-folder 3, Item 4)
- Map of Federick County, 1965 (Map-folder 3, Item 5)
- Map of Montgonery County and DC, 1950 (Map-folder 3, Item 6)
- Map of Hancock, W. VA - MD - PA, 1927 (Map-folder 3, Item 7)
- Map of Washington County, 1968 (Map-folder 3, Item 8)
- Map of HancockC and O Canal Topographical map 19 - Cherry Run, 1951 (Map-folder 3, Item 9)